Guide to the ILGWU. Local 89 minutes, 1919-1968.
ILGWU. Local 89 minutes,
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
ILGWU. Local 89 minutes, 1919-1968.
5780/064
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 89 (New York, N.Y.)
4 linear feet
Minutes
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
This collection contains records of International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 64, the Italian Dressmakers' Union of New York City. Materials include meeting minutes.
ILGWU ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the “new unionism,” the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers’ strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers’ strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the “protocol of peace,” a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Local 89 of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), also known as the Italian Dressmakers' Union, was based in New York, New York.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
This collection contains records of International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 64, the Italian Dressmakers' Union of New York City. Materials include meeting minutes.
SUBJECTS
Names:
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 89 (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Women's clothing industry--United States.; Women's clothing industry--New York (State)--New York.; Labor unions--Clothing workers--United States.; Labor unions--Clothing workers--New York (State)--New York.; Clothing workers--United States.; Clothing workers--New York (State)--New York.; Industrial relations--United States.; Industrial relations--New York (State)--New York.
Form and Genre Terms:
Records.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
RELATED MATERIALS
5780. ILGWU records
5780/023. ILGWU. Local 89. Luigi Antonini correspondence
5780/024. ILGWU. Local 89 records
5780/213. ILGWU. Local 89-22-1 records
NOTES
"Permanent deposit"
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Series I contains the minutes of several of Local 89's committees, as well as membership meetings from 1919 to 1923. Series II contains minutes of the Executive Committee's meetings from 1917 to 1974. Series III contains minutes of the Finance Committee's meetings from 1923 to 1973. Series IV contains minutes of the Relief and Emergency Welfare Fund Committee's meetings from 1945 to 1968.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Committee minutes, 1919-1971
Series II. Executive board minutes, 1919-1974
Series III. Finance committee, 1923-1973
Series IV. Relief and Emergency Welfare Fund Committee, 1945-1968
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Committee minutes, 1919-1971
  - Advisory Board. Main District and Branch Offices Minutes., 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    May 1934 - December 1935
  - Appeal Committee., 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    June 1934 - December 1941
  - District Membership Meeting. Main Office., 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    August 1934 - June 1935
  - General Council Minutes, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1. April 23, 1937 - March 25, 1942
  - General Council Minutes, 1942-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    2. May 29, 1942 - April 22, 1959
  - General Membership Meeting of Main and Branch Offices., 1927-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - IDWU Summer Colony, Inc. Board of Directors Minutes., 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    October 14, 1920 - April 30, 1923
  - Main District Minutes, 1936-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1. January 6, 1936 - October 18, 1956
  - Main District Minutes, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    2. 1968 - 1971
  - Meeting of Standing Committees., 1919-1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    December 1, 1919 - April 30, 1923
  - Membership Meeting Minutes., 1919-1923 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    November 26, 1919 - April 23, 1923
- Series II. Executive board minutes, 1919-1974
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1919-1923 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1927-1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    May 1927 - April 1932
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1932-1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    May 1932 - December 1935
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    January 3, 1936 - March 19, 1937
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    April 22, 1937 - December 16, 1938
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    January 1939 - December 1940
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    January 3, 1941 - December 17, 1943
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1944-1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    January 7, 1944 - December 19, 1944
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    January 12, 1945 - December 27, 1946
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    January 17, 1947 - December 17, 1948
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    January 14, 1949 - December 8, 1950
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    January 5, 1951 - December 19, 1952
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    February 1, 1953 - December 17, 1954
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    January 14, 1955 - December 28, 1956
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    February 8, 1957 - March 6, 1959
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    March 21, 1959 - March 23, 1962
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    March 31, 1962 - February 19, 1965
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    March 10, 1965 - February 27, 1968
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    March 8, 1968 - February 2, 1971
  - Executive Board. Minutes., 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    February 23, 1971 - January 8, 1974
- Series III. Finance committee, 1923-1973
  - Executive Board Finance Committee Minutes., 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    May 1, 1923 - April 30, 1924
  - Finance Committee, 1927-1937 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    1. March 16, 1927 - December 7, 1937
  - Finance Committee, 1938-1942 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    2. January 1938 - April 1942
  - Finance Committee, 1942-1952 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    3. May 25, 1942 - March 5, 1952
  - Finance Committee, 1952-1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    4. May 19, 1952 - December 4, 1961
  - Finance Committee, 1962-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    5. January 8, 1962 - December 5, 1972
  - Finance Committee Minutes., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    January 2, 1973
- Series IV. Relief and Emergency Welfare Fund Committee, 1945-1968
  - Relief and Emergency Welfare Fund Committee Minutes, 1945-1951 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    1. January 6, 1945 - December 20, 1951
  - Emergency Welfare Fund Committee Minutes, 1952-1956 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    2. March 3, 1952 - December 5, 1956
  - Emergency Welfare Fund Committee Minutes, 1957-1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    3. February 13, 1957 - February 5, 1962
  - Emergency Welfare Fund Administrative Committee., 1962-1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    April 27, 1962 - February 1, 1968